Guide to the Montrose Singers/Gay Men's Chorus Collection, 1979-2010 MS 616
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Montrose Singers/Gay Men's Chorus Collection
1979-2010
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Houston Gay Men's Chorus
MS 616
0.1 Linear Feet (1 folder containing a thumb drive)
2.45 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0616aip_001 (2.45 GB)
This collection consists of interview transcripts, audio files, program images, and historical documents compiled by JD Doyle. (1 Flash Drive)
Biographical/Historical Note
Originally, the Montrose Marching Band was founded for the March on Washington on October 14, 1979. Andy Mills, a member of the band, worked to preserve the band after the conclusion of the march. In its place, he founded the Montrose Symphonic Band and the Montrose Singers in 1979. It was one of the first five gay men's choruses to be founded in the United States.
John-Michael Albert, a published composer with a B.A. in Music from the University of the South and a Master of Music in Conducting from the Moores School of Music at the University of Houston, was also a very early and influential member of the Montrose Singers. For 15 years, starting in 1981, he composed choral pieces for and conducted the chorus.
The Montrose Singers were among the twelve choruses that founded the Gay and Lesbian Association of Choruses (GALA) and have since perforemd alongside other choruses in the Houston community. Between 1988 and 1995, the group sang alongside HeartSong, a lesbian chorus group also from Houston.
In 1992, the group changed its name to the Houston Gay Men's Chorus. The group still exists today and is now part of a larger umbrella organization called Bayou City Performing Arts.
--Taken from http://www.queermusicheritage.us/nov2010m3.html and http://www.mygayhouston.com/listings/Bayou-City-Performing-Arts/23174/
Scope and Contents Note
This collection consists of seven series, which contain audio from performances by the Montrose Singers, copies of programs from various shows, photographs of the group, and a brief history of the group. More specifically, included is a timeline of the group's performances, interview transcripts from the Gay Music Heritage show in 2010, and an account of the problems faced by the choir in the late 1980s. Additionally this series contains audio from concerts performed alongside HeartSong, a Houston lesbian chorus, and programs from those events.
All audio, visual, and textual media exist in digital formats. Please Series VIII for more information.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research. Please be aware that this collection only exists in digital form. Please see Series VIII for more instructions regarding access.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by JD Doyle, August 2013.
Accruals
Additional materials are not expected for this collection.
Index Terms
Subjects
Music; LGBTQ people
Document Types
digital audio formats; photographs; programs (documents)
Places
Texas -- History
Subjects (Corporations)
Montrose Singers; Houston Gay Men's Chorus
- Series I: Chorus History, 175014
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains a complete list of directors, a written history of the chorus by a member, and a timeline of performances.
  - Directors List, 175063 (Folder 1, Item 1)
  - GMC Houston Early History, 175064 (Folder 1, Item 2)
  - Director and Performance Timeline, 175065 (Folder 1, Item 3)
  - Original Organization of Flash Drive, 175066 (Folder 1, Item 4)
- Series II: Director Andy Mills, 1979-1982, 174664
  This series contains audio and programs for performances by the Montrose Singers under the direction of Andy Mills, the first director of the group.
  - Audio, 1980-1982; 174997 (Folder 2, Subfolder 1)
  - Programs, 1980; 174998 (Folder 2, Subfolder 2)
- Series III: Director Rex Gillet, 1990s, 175015
  This series contains audio and programs for performances by the Montrose Singers under the direction of Rex Gillet.
  - Audio, 1980-1999; 175067 (Folder 3, Subfolder 1)
  - Programs, 1980-1999; 175017 (Folder 3, Subfolder 2)
- Series IV: Heartsong, 1988-1995, 174725
  HeartSong was a predominately lesbian Houston chorus that performed with the Montrose Singers in the early 90s and disbanded in 1995. This series includes audio files, images, and documents relating to the Montrose Singers' shared performances with HeartSong.
  - Documents, 1995; 174995 (Folder 4, Subfolder 1)
    General Note
    Contains a brief history of HeartSong, as well as a dedication from their final performance alongside the Montrose Singers.
  - Images, 1980-1990; 174996 (Folder 4, Subfolder 2)
    This folder contians programs from various performances by HeartSong, as well as tape covers from professional recordings of the group.
  - Audio, 1988-1990; 174999 (Folder 4, Subfolder 3)
    This folder contains several recordings of HeartSong performances in the late 1980s and early 1990s.
- Series V: Houston - Gay Men's Chorus Queer Music Heritage Show, 2010, 174736
  This series contains recordings, images, and interview transcripts from the Houston Gay Men's Chorus' performance in the 2010 Queer Music Heritage Show.
  - Director Linus Lerner Interview, 174737 (Folder 5, Subfolder 1)
    This folder contains audio, visual, and textual materials related to an interview with director Dr. Linus Lerner for the Queer Music Heritage Show.
  - Director Andy Mills Interview, 174738 (Folder 5, Subfolder 2)
    This folder contains audio, visual, and textual materials related to an interview with the Montrose Singers' ex-director and founder Andy Mills for the Queer Music Heritage Show.
  - Show Materials, 2010; 174739 (Folder 5, Subfolder 3)
    This folder contains audio, visual, and descriptive materials of the Houston Gay Men's Chorus' performance in Houston's 2010 Queer Music Heritage Show.
  - Richard Hudkins Interview, 175001 (Folder 5, Subfolder 4)
    This folder contains audio, visual, and textual materials related to an interview with chorus member Richard Hudkins for the Queer Music Heritage Show.
  - David Gebo Interview, 175002 (Folder 5, Subfolder 5)
    This folder contains audio, visual, and textual materials related to an interview with chorus member David Gebo for the Queer Music Heritage Show.
- Series VI: Photographs, 1980-2010; 175003
  This series contains photos of members, tape covers, and programs throughout the history of the Montrose Singers/Gay Men's Chorus.
  - Images, 1980s; 175004 (Folder 6, Subfolder 1)
  - Christmas, 1980; 175005 (Folder 6, Subfolder 2)
  - Misc Images, 1980-2010; 175006 (Folder 6, Subfolder 3)
  - Pride Concert, 1982; 175007 (Folder 6, Subfolder 4)
  - Pride Concert, June 19, 1999; 175008 (Folder 6, Subfolder 5)
  - Sen Jack Ogg - Gov for a Day, October 2, 1981; 175009 (Folder 6, Subfolder 6)
  - Sen Rodney Ellis - Gov for a Day, April 8, 2000; 175010 (Folder 6, Subfolder 7)
  - St. Stephens Episcopal Church, September 1985; 175011 (Folder 6, Subfolder 8)
  - Tape Covers, 1981-1999; 175012 (Folder 6, Subfolder 9)
  - Tower Theater, December 1980; 175013 (Folder 6, Subfolder 10)
- Series VII: Programs, 1980-2001; 175018
  Each program folder in this series contains scans of individual pages from the program for the respective concert.
  - First Concert, 1980; 175020 (Folder 7, Subfolder 1)
  - Ceremony of the Carols, 1981; 175021 (Folder 7, Subfolder 2)
  - Holiday Festival, December 16, 1983; 175022 (Folder 7, Subfolder 3)
  - Orchestra Texas, 1983; 175023 (Folder 7, Subfolder 4)
  - Day of Remembrance, June 27, 1985; 175024 (Folder 7, Subfolder 5)
  - Texas Fahrten, May 11, 1986; 175025 (Folder 7, Subfolder 6)
  - Lone Star Band, October 28, 1989; 175026 (Folder 7, Subfolder 7)
  - Lone Star band-GPW, June 24, 1989; 175027 (Folder 7, Subfolder 8)
  - Day of Rembrance, June 21, 1990; 175028 (Folder 7, Subfolder 9)
  - HeartSong, 1990; 175029 (Folder 7, Subfolder 10)
  - Lone Star Band + TCC, April 21, 1990; 175030 (Folder 7, Subfolder 11)
  - Season For Us All, December 15, 1990; 175031 (Folder 7, Subfolder 12)
  - Tenth Anniversary, June 17, 1990; 175032 (Folder 7, Subfolder 13)
  - Happy Together, October 6, 1991; 175033 (Folder 7, Subfolder 14)
  - Texas Sing Out, March 16, 1991; 175034 (Folder 7, Subfolder 15)
  - Capital City, May 17, 1992; 175035 (Folder 7, Subfolder 16)
  - Our Time, June 20, 1992; 175036 (Folder 7, Subfolder 17)
  - Season for us all, December 12, 1992; 175037 (Folder 7, Subfolder 18)
  - New Orleans, June 19, 1993; 175038 (Folder 7, Subfolder 19)
  - Out Together & Proud, June 26, 1993; 175039 (Folder 7, Subfolder 20)
  - Season for us all, December 11, 1993; 175040 (Folder 7, Subfolder 21)
  - HeartSong, October 15, 1994; 175041 (Folder 7, Subfolder 22)
  - Season for us all, December, 16, 1994; 175042 (Folder 7, Subfolder 23)
  - TF&TL, July 2, 1994; 175043 (Folder 7, Subfolder 24)
  - Love Is All It Takes, March 25, 1995; 175044 (Folder 7, Subfolder 25)
  - Proud Out Loud, June 24, 1995; 175045 (Folder 7, Subfolder 26)
  - Stories of the Season, December 8, 1995; 175046 (Folder 7, Subfolder 27)
  - GALA Fest Tampa, July 1996; 175047 (Folder 7, Subfolder 28)
  - Simple Gifts, December 14, 1996; 175048 (Folder 7, Subfolder 29)
  - Simple Pleasures, June 21, 1997; 175049 (Folder 7, Subfolder 30)
  - Travel for the Holidays, December 6, 1997; 175050 (Folder 7, Subfolder 31)
  - Pride Band 20th Anniversary, 1998; 175051 (Folder 7, Subfolder 32)
  - Sing of Love, March 28, 1998; 175052 (Folder 7, Subfolder 33)
  - Way Out West, December 5, 1998; 175053 (Folder 7, Subfolder 34)
  - I Write the Songs, March 27, 1999; 175054 (Folder 7, Subfolder 35)
  - In the Spirit, December 4, 1999; 175055 (Folder 7, Subfolder 36)
  - Family Values, March 25, 2000; 175056 (Folder 7, Subfolder 37)
  - It's a Wonderful Life, December 2, 2000; 175057 (Folder 7, Subfolder 38)
  - That's Entertainment, July 16, 2001; 175058 (Folder 7, Subfolder 39)
  - Band-Stars Across America, September 29, 1991; 175059 (Folder 7, Subfolder 40)
  - Early Programs, 1980-1981; 175060 (Folder 7, Subfolder 41)
  - HeartSong, 1988-1990; 175061 (Folder 7, Subfolder 42)
  - Lone Star Band-Stars Across America, September 29, 1991; 175062 (Folder 7, Subfolder 43)
- Series VIII: Digital files, 2014
  Still images (jpg), audio (mp3), and text files (pdf) representing the work and history of the Montrose Singers/Gay Men's Chorus and HeartSong.